<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Lab 02 - CodeIgniter Intro
-->
<lab status="beta">
    <!-- Activity metadata ... override anything from the course or organizer -->
    
    <!-- The meat of the presentation -->
    <slide title="Lab Goals" layout="normal">
        <p>The purpose of this lab was to introduce you to
            CodeIgniter and the workflow for working with
            webapps.
            It looks like I have an incorrect understanding of the
            background you bring to this lab, both in terms of concepts
            as well as previous experience. I am revising the original lab 2,
            splitting it over two labs.</p>
        <p>What worked well was my walking the group through the 
            "lab preparation", which took pretty much the entire lab
            (rather than the 15 minutes I expected!).</p>
        <p>Revised purpose: Process Preparation</p>
        <p>Suggestion: you may want to skim the slideshow first,
            before working your way through it.</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Teams" layout="normal">
        <p>This is a pair lab, sharing a single repository, but with each 
            team member using
            their own github account and computer.</p>
        <p>If you insist on working on your own, you will need to setup a second github
            account, and use two machines, to get the full benefit (and marks) of the lab.</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Submission" layout="normal">
        <p>Your lab will result in a github repository, ready for the
            next lab (which will be the "real" conversion from a 
            static site to a CodeIgniter webapp).
            If you work ahead, and complete the conversion, you
            are welcome to have that in your repository for lab 2, but I will
            treat the resulting webapp as part of your lab 3.</p>
                
        <p>Submit a readme *text* file, or a submission comment, to the lab dropbox.
            It should contain a link to your github repository. Only
            one of these is needed, for the pair of students.</p>
        <p>Each of the students should also submit their httpd-vhosts.conf file.</p>
        <p>Due: three days after your lab, eg. Thursday lab period will have theirs
            due Sunday, Jan 17, 17:30 PST</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Preview" layout="normal">
        <p>There are a few things to sort out before diving into the CodeIgniter 
            lab itself (which is now lab 3) - "process":</p>
        <ul>
            <li>your D2L group</li>
            <li>get github setup</li>
            <li>clone your repo</li>
            <li>add local domains to your system</li>
            <li>configure your AMP setup (virtual hosting)</li>
            <li>make a CodeIgniter starter</li>
            <li>incorporate the starter into your repository</li>
        </ul>
        <p>I originally referenced some devops tutorials for these, but that proved
            confusing. I will walk you through it, instead.</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Prep - D2L Group" layout="normal">
        <p>This lab is for group submission, and I have set up groups for each
            set, with up to two members, self-enrolled.</p>
        <p>Choose a partner for this lab. One of you should enrol in a group,
            to claim it, and the other should join that group.</p>
        <p>If you inadvertently end up paired with the wrong teammate,
            let me know during lab and I can fix that.</p>
        <p>The groups are for this lab only, and do not have to be maintained for 
            the assignments. You will be setting up assignment teams next week.</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Prep - Github" layout="normal">
        <p>If you are a team of one, you will need to create a second github account
            for yourself, and plan to use a different machine for each acocunt. 
            We want to replicate a collaborative environment, with two developers
            sharing a common repository.</p>
        <p>One of you should fork the starter repository for the lab, and they
            should then add their teammate as a collaborator, with write permission.
            You should both be able to push code to the repo!</p>
        <p>You are welcome to change the repo name, in its Github settings, if
            that makes more sense to you. It will still show as a fork of the starter.</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Prep - Cloning" layout="normal">
        <p>Each of you will want to clone the shared repository to your development system,
            be it your laptop or one of the lab machines.</p>
        <p>Clone it into the *htdocs* (or equivalent) folder within your AMP stack.</p>
        <p>The foldername can be anything meaningful to you, for instance "comp4711lab02",
            or you can stick with "example-gallery" all the way through.</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Prep - Post-Cloning" layout="normal">
        <p>After cloning, you should be able to see the starter's image gallery
            using the URL "localhost/comp4711lab02/public". This is only
            to make sure it is in the proper place, and not what you will use for
            development.</p>
        <p>You do NOT want to have to use a URL like "localhost/comp4711/labs/lab02/public" -
            that is too many folders deep!!</p>
        <p>I trust you remembered to inject the port number you assigned
            during AMP setup, if other than 80 ... for instance,
            "localhost:4711/comp4711lab02/public"</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Prep - Local Domain" layout="normal">
        <p>We want to use domain based hosting, so that media references
            work properly in spite of apparent folder names in an URL.
            The apparent foloder names can confuse your browser if you use sub-sontroller methods.</p>
        <p>For instance, "/product/buy/shoes/1" looks to the browser like it is inside the
            website folder "product/buy/shoes", but there is no such folder. Relative image
            references, such as "../assets/images/blah" will not work properly.</p>
        <p>Add one or more local domain names to your <code>hosts</code> file.
            This could be names that you remap each week as needed, for instance "comp4711.local",
            or you could add a new domain each week, eg. "4711lab02.local", "4711lab03.local", etc.</p>
        <p>Do this by adding a line to the end of your <code>hosts</code> file, like<br/>
            <code>127.0.0.1 comp4711.local project.local 4711lab25.local</code>
        </p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Prep - Virtual Hosting" layout="normal">
        <p>Configure your Apache virtual hosting, found in <code>httpd-vhosts.conf</code>
            inside the <code>extra</code> folder of your Apache configuration folder.</p>
        <p>Your AMP comes with a couple of VirtualHost definitions, that are to be
            used as examples only - they are not real, and can be deleted or commented out once done.</p>
        <p>You want to end up with several VirtualHosts - one for the *default*, and
            one for each local domain.</p>
        <p>Each VirtualHost definition needs a ServerName, eg <code>comp4711.local</code>,
            and then the DocumentRoot that domain should be mapped to (with no trailing slash), for instance
            <code>/opt/lampstack-5.5.30-1/apache2/htdocs/comp4711lab02</code>.</p>
        <p>The first VirtualHost defined in the config file is special - it is
            the AMP base installation, eg. the Bitnami start page.</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Prep - CodeIgniter Setup" layout="normal">
        <p>Download CodeIgniter, the current release from 
            https://github.com/bcit-ci/CodeIgniter/archive/3.0.4.zip</p>
        <p>Extract this inside your downloads folder - you should end up with a 
            <code>CodeIgniter-3.0.4</code> folder, containing <code>application</code>,
            <code>system</code> and <code>user_guide</code> folders, as well as
            an <code>index.php</code> and some other files.
        </p>
        <p>Move the <code>system</code> folder inside your <code>htdocs</code>,
            and rename it to <code>system3</code>.</p>
        <p>If you want to keep the user guide handy for local reference, move the
            <code>user_guide</code> folder somewhere you can easily find it, for 
            instance your desktop, and possibly renamed suitably. If you prefer to
            read the user guide online, then just delete the <code>user_guide</code> folder.</p>
        <p>The stuff remaining in your <code>CodeIgniter-3.0.4</code> folder will
            be your "CodeIgniter starter" folder, for new projects. You might want
            to rename it appropriately.</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Prep - Prepared" layout="normal">
        <p>Walking you through this in lab will have pretty much consumed
            the lab time, but you are now ready for the next lab,
            and you should be comfortable with the process.</p>
        <p>You should have your <code>htdocs</code> folder ready to roll,
            with the CodeIgniter <code>system3</code> framework folder inside it,
            as well as your lab's project folder.
        </p>
        <p>You will have a CoeIgniter starter folder, the contents of which can 
            be copied into a new (cloned) CodeIgniter project.</p>
        <p>You will have a local domain defined and virtual hosting setup in
            your Apache.</p>
        <p>You may have the CodeIgniter user guide in a folder on your desktop 
            for convenience.</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Marking Guideline" layout="normal">
        <p>This lab will be marked out of 10, as follows:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Proper fork and collaborator setup of your repo (3)</li>
            <li>Reasonable vhost configuration (3)</li>
            <li>Correct repo content - starter repo with the CI starter integrated (3)</li>
            <li>Consideration for your pain and suffering - no bonus marks! (1)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>The grading scheme above is meant to reflect the work required to result in
            each of the final results.</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Disclaimer" layout="normal">
        <p>We will not necessarily be following "best practices" throughout this lab.</p>
        <p>Our focus is on "baby steps", that will lead to best practices over the
            next few labs.</p>
    </slide>

</lab>
