<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Lab 05 - Views, libraries & helpers
-->
<lab status="beta">
    <!-- Activity metadata ... override anything from the course or organizer -->
    
    <!-- The meat of the presentation -->
    <slide title="Lab Goals" layout="normal">
        <p>The purpose of this lab is to expose you to one way
            to incorporate an addin for your CodeIgniter webapp.</p>
        <p>I originally had more comprehensive plans, incorporating
            a helper and adding some maintenance pages, but decided that
            those were not appropriate at this point.
            The <code>formfields_helper</code> that I mentioned in class is in the
            starter file, in case you wish to explore it on your own.</p>
        <p>Suggestion: you may want to skim the slideshow first,
            before working your way through it.</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Submission" layout="normal">
        <p>Your lab is tutorial "ci-normal05", and will be completed in a github repository.
            This will be your (forked) starter-caboose repo. 
        </p>
        <p>Follow gitflow workflow practices (forking &amp; branching).</p>
        <p>You may work on your own or use pair programming.</p>
        <p>Please make sure that your work is in the "master" branch
            or your repository, when done, and that any other branch(es) have
            been merged into it.</p>
        <p>Submit a readme to the lab dropbox, with a link to your github repository.</p>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Lab Marking Guideline" layout="normal">
        <p>I have chosen to keep this lab purposefully easy, so as
            to give you all an opportunity to complete it without
            impacting your preparations for midterm week.</p>
        <p>Marks awarded as follows:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>Incorporating Caboose into the master view template ... 2</li>
            <li>Adding and configuring the rating widget for use with Caboose ... 3</li>
            <li>Applying the rating widget to the two views described ... 2</li>
            <li>Observing proper gitflow workflow (forking, branching, signing,
            not messing up the database config) ... 3</li>
        </ul>
    </slide>

</lab>
