<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Models in a Nutshell
-->
<lesson status="beta">

    <slide title="Sorry" layout="normal">
        <div class="left">
            <p>I was not happy with today's presentation.
                I ran out of time preparing it, and
                cobbled the pieces together without
                thinking it through as well as I planned to :(</p>
            <p>I have added suitable graphics, and a few
                missing slides, as well as the "message" for each.
                I hope this makes more sense :-/</p>
        </div>
        <div class="right">
            <img src="/pix/lessons/nutshell/nuts12.jpg"/>
        </div>
    </slide>

    <slide title="#ModelsMatter" layout="normal">
        <div class="left">
            <p>Models are our encapsulation of the data that needs
                to be used and/or persisted in order to fulfill the
                usecases for an application, web or otherwise.</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Properties (per class diagrams)</li>
                <li>aggregation (per ERD relationships)</li>
                <li>business logic (per usecases)</li>
                <li>validation (per usecases)</li>
            </ul>
            <b>Models are unavoidable!</b>
        </div>
        <div class="right">
            <img src="/pix/lessons/nutshell/nuts1.png"/>
        </div>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Modeling Small &amp; Large" layout="normal">
        <div class="left">
            <p>We have models for entities
                (components, table rows).</p>
            <p>We have models for aggregations of entities
                (collection, repository, table).</p>
            <b>We have to model both of these!</b>
        </div>
        <div class="right">
            <p>We need to worry about all of these:</p>
            <img src="/pix/lessons/nutshell/nuts7.png"/>
        </div>

    </slide>


    <slide title="Object-Relational Mapping" layout="normal"  tag="tag1">
        <div class="left">
            <p>Most data, like it or not, is stored in relational databases.</p>
            <p>Most application code, like it or not, is built using O-O languages.</p>
            <p>In the broadest sense, "ORM" refers to whatever you use
                to bridge these two, translating  between them.</p>
            <b>The problem is not that we have some form of ORM, but
                that different frameworks and different cultures implement
                so differently, yet using the same name!</b>
        </div>
        <div class="right">
            <img src="/pix/lessons/nutshell/nuts3.gif"/>
        </div>
    </slide>

    <slide title="#JobsMatter" layout="normal"  tag="tag1">
        <div class="left">
            <p>There are two distinct cultures at play: web and enterprise.</p>
            <p>Most of you will either work in the enterprise world, or you will have
                to deal with it as business "partners".</p>
            <b>Like it or not, you need to understand the enterprise perspective!</b>
        </div>
        <div class="right">
            <img src="/pix/lessons/nutshell/nuts2.jpg"/>
        </div>
    </slide>

    <slide title="#PhpMatters?" layout="normal"  tag="tag1">
        <div class="left">
            <p>Web development (not just PHP) has issues
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>weak typing</li>
                <li>scripting vs O-O</li>
                <li>over-reliance on RDB</li>
                <li>different term interpretations</li>
            </ul>
            <b>PHP isn't perfect, but its low entry barrier
                makes it a suitable choice for most webapps!</b>
        </div>
        <div class="right">
            <img src="/pix/lessons/nutshell/nuts4.jpg"/>
        </div>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Modeling Layers" layout="normal">
        <div class="left">
            <p>Each of these builds on the earlier layers
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Database driver &amp; adapters</li>
                <li>Object model for this (data access layer)</li>
                <li>Data Mapper (MY_Model?)</li>
                <li>Entity models (Active Record)</li>
                <li>Application models</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                An enterprise perspective is shown to the right.</p>
            <b>Enterprise culture expects all of these to be implemented,
                while web culture picks and chooses those to!</b>
        </div>
        <div class="right">
            <img src="/pix/lessons/nutshell/nuts9.jpg"/>
        </div>
    </slide>
    
    <slide title="Model View Adapter?" layout="normal">
        <div class="left">
            <p>Model-View-Adapter is a popular variation of MVC, chosen
                because it avoids the problem of a view being
                notified of a model state change.</p>
            <p>The controller, before calling a model mutator method,
                might register an observer callback, and adjust
                the view it returns if the model state changes.
            </p>
            <b>The view is unaware of the source of data, and the model is
                unaware of what will be done with its data!</b>
        </div>
        <div class="right">
            <img src="/pix/lessons/nutshell/nuts8.png"/>
        </div>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Model View View-Model?" layout="normal">
        <div class="left">
            <p>Model-View-View-Model is another variation of MVC, chosen
                because it "solves" the problem of a view being
                notified of a model state change.</p>
            <p>The hiccup? This choice needs client-side logic
                (for instance AngularJS) to act as an intermediary
                between the user interface and the "backend".
            </p>
            <p>The backend (us) then need to provide controller entry
                points for the ViewModel to request data from, or to
                provide data to, typically using AJAX.</p>
            <b>Our webapp is simpler, because logic is moved to the
                client, which is arguably not our problem!</b>
        </div>
        <div class="right">
            <img src="/pix/lessons/nutshell/nuts6.jpg"/>
        </div>
    </slide>

    <slide title="Model Persistance" layout="normal">
        <div class="left">
            <p>There were some questions about "why" XML
                or other non-SQL "models".</p>
            <p>The Data Mapper layer has no bias towards
                SQL in its API. Using adapters for 
                different persistance methods makes the
                Data Mapper more flexible.
            </p>
            <p>XML, in particular, offers a closer state match
                to object complexity, not having to store unlike
                things in separate tables.</p>
            <b>Where to store data becomes a deployment decision,
                not a development one!</b>
        </div>
        <div class="right">
            <p>A real-world example: <a href="https://flysystem.thephpleague.com/"
                                         target="_blank">FlySystem</a>. While not database specific,
                it illustrates using adapters to persist stuff in
                a variety of different ways!</p>
            <img src="/pix/lessons/nutshell/nuts11.png"/>
        </div>
    </slide>


</lesson>
