<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Lesson 02 - MVC Framework Introduction
-->
<lesson status="v1.1">
	<!-- Activity metadata ... override anything from the course or organizer -->

	<!-- Agenda -->
	<slide title="Agenda" layout="normal">
		<p>We talked about MVC frameworks in general last week.
			This lesson provides a closer look at CodeIgniter.</p>
		<ol>
			<li>
				<a href="#{tag1}">Project Files</a>
			</li>
			<li>
				<a href="#{tag2}">Models</a>
			</li>
			<li>
				<a href="#{tag3}">Controllers</a>
			</li>
			<li>
				<a href="#{tag4}">Views</a>
			</li>
			<li>
				<a href="#{tag5}">Support Components</a>
			</li>
			<li>
				<a href="#{tag6}">Your CI Webapp!</a>
			</li>
		</ol>
	</slide>


	<!-- Normal slides -->

	<slide title="Setup" layout="normal">
		<h1>Setup</h1>
		<p>This lesson mentions source code files from
			the <a href="https://github.com/jedi-academy/example-contacts" target="_blank">
				Example Contacts
			</a> demo webapp. Please download that project first, and extract
			it locally, so that you can refer to the source files during the lesson.
		</p>
		<p>If you want to run the demo app on your system, you will need to
			setup a MySQL database, <code>comp4711</code>, using the SQL script inside the
			project at <code>data/contacts.sql</code>. You would also have to specify
			your mysql password in the database configuration file, 
			<code>application/config/database.php</code>.</p>
		<p>Disclaimer: the demo webapp is not useful as a webapp - it is
			only intended to illustrate the different pieces of a
			CodeIgniter webapp!</p>
	</slide>

	<slide title="1. Project Files" layout="normal" tag="tag1">
		<div class="left">
			<p>A CodeIgniter project contains application logic
				(inside <code>application</code>), the framework code
				(inside <code>system</code>), and public-facing
				files (inside <code>public</code>, which
				is the intended "document root").
				Nothing outside the <code>public</code> folder is
				directly accessible, and a small webapp could contain
				data in a separate folder too.
			</p>
			<p>Inside <code>public</code> are two important files:
				<ul>
					<li>
						<code>index.php</code> *is* the
						front controller, i.e. entry point.</li>
					<li>
						<code>.htaccess</code>is an Apache configuration file, to
						eliminate the need to explicitly have "index.php" in
						URLs.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div class="right">
			<br/>
			<img class="scale" width="249" height="361" src="/pix/lessons/2/2-2.png"/>
		</div>
	</slide>

	<slide title="Class Loader" layout="normal">
		<p>CodeIgniter has its own class loader.</p>
		<p>It uses the folder structure to locate classes (per MVC)</p>
		<pre>
			<code>
				$this->load->model('customers');
				$this->customers->get(...);
			</code>
		</pre>
		<p>The loader enforces naming conventions too.
			For instance, you will find that class source files
			follow the "UCfirst" convention.</p>
	</slide>

	<slide title="Routing" layout="normal">
		<p>CodeIgniter normally routes requests to controllers by
			convention, i.e. using the URI segment and looking in the controllers
			folder. Other frameworks often handle routing a bit differently.</p>
		<p>The framework will determine the appropriate controller class
			and method to execute, to satisfy the incoming request.</p>
		<p>CodeIgniter will inject references to the framework
			components, as properties of your controller, as well
			as references to your app components as you load them. 
			You may have noticed this on the previous slide, with <code>$this->load</code>
			and <code>$this->customers</code>.
		</p>
	</slide>

	<slide title="2. Models" layout="normal" tag="tag2">
		<div class="left">
			<p>One of the cornerstones of MVC, <strong>models</strong> encapsulate data sources or entities.</p>
			<p>Each model is a class that wraps a data source.</p>
			<p>A data source could be an RDB table, or an aggregation such as
				orders with item details. It could even be connected to the
				server's file system.</p>
			<p>CodeIgniter models are collections, rather than component
				models for single entities. CodeIgniter encourages the Active Record design
				pattern (which says you build CRUD methods into models),
				but doesn't require it.</p>
		</div>
		<div class="right">
			<br/>
			<img class="scale" width="279" height="386" src="/pix/lessons/2/2-6.png"/>
		</div>
	</slide>

	<slide title="Query Builder" layout="normal">
		<div class="left">
			<p>CodeIgniter comes with a QueryBuilder library,
				to make it easier to access your databases.</p>
				<p>An example is shown to the right. The specific
				database engine has been abstracted, so your
				logic works with different data stores.</p>
		</div>
		<div class="right">
			<pre>
				<code>
$this-&gt;db-&gt;select('*')-&gt;from('my_table')
	-&gt;group_start()
	-&gt;where('a', 'a')
	-&gt;or_group_start()
	-&gt;where('b', 'b')
	-&gt;where('c', 'c')
	-&gt;group_end()
	-&gt;group_end()
	-&gt;where('d', 'd')
	-&gt;get();                
				</code>
			</pre>
		</div>
	</slide>

	<slide title="Model Classes" layout="normal">
		<div class="left">
			<p>In CodeIgniter, models are classes that extend CI_Model.</p>
			<p>Each data source, eg. RDB table, usually has its own model.</p>
			<p>A common practice is to use a "heavy model" philosophy,
			where the bulk of business logic is inside model classes,
			in addition to data retrieval and storage.</p>
		</div>
		<div class="right">
			<pre>
				<code>
public class Orders extends CI_Model {
	public function add_item($code, $quantity) {...}
	public function calc_total() {...}
}
				</code>
			</pre>
		</div>
	</slide>

	<slide title="Base Model" layout="normal">
		<p>You can provide your own base model, with
			common methods. See <code>application/core/MY_Model</code> in the example webapp.
			The <code>application/core</code> folder holds any classes you make that
			build on those built into the framework, and you can configure the prefix (<code>MY_</code>)
			that you use.</p>
		<p>This could be used to provide a simple object-relational map.</p>
		<p>Sample properties: $_tableName, $_keyField</p>
		<p>Sample methods: create() get($key), add($record), 
			update($record), delete($key), exists($key)</p>
			<p>The result is that a simple model, with basic CRUD methods only,
				becomes as simple as that in the demo, <code>application/models/Contacts</code>
			</p>
	</slide>

 
	<slide title="3. Controllers" layout="normal" tag="tag3">
		<div class="left">
			<p>Another cornerstone of MVC, <strong>controllers</strong> handle incoming requests.</p>
			<p>A Controller serves as an intermediary between the Model, 
				the View, and any other resources needed to process an 
				HTTP request and generate a web page.</p>
				<p>Our demo app only has the one controller, <code>application/controllers/Welcome</code></p>
		</div>
		<div class="right">
			<br/>
			<img class="scale" width="240" height="164" src="/pix/lessons/2/2-8.png"/>
		</div>
	</slide>

	<slide title="CI Controllers" layout="normal">
		<div class="left">
			<p>In CI, controllers are classes that extend CI_Controller, or 
				your base controller with common functionality.</p>
				<p>Our base controller implements view templating, through its <code>render()</code> method</p>
				<p>See <code>application/core/MY_Controller</code></p>
		</div>
		<div class="right">
			<br/>
			<img class="scale" width="240" height="174" src="/pix/lessons/2/2-9.png"/>
		</div>
	</slide>

	<slide title="App Controllers" layout="normal">
		<p>Each of your webapp controllers builds on your base controller.</p>
		<p>Normally, each usecase has its own controller.</p>
		<p>Additionally, controllers or subcontrollers are used for services.</p>
		<p>An upcoming lesson will explore controllers in more detail!</p>
	</slide>

	<slide title="Controller Methods" layout="normal">
		<p>URLs are segment based, with the pattern "example.com/class/function/parm1/parm2".</p>
		<p>The <code>index()</code> method is the default handler function, while other public
			methods are treated as sub-controllers.</p>
		<p>Parameters are passed positionally.</p>
		<p>An example: given the URI "/products/shoes/sandals/123", the segments could
			be interpreted as the controller (Products), method inside it (shoes), and
			then two parameters passed to that method (sandals and 123).</p>
		<p>Confusion is possible ...
			"application/controllers/business/work" could refer to the "work" method
			inside the Business controller, or it
			could refer to the Work controller inside the business subfolder
			with the controllers!</p>
	</slide>


	<slide title="4. Views" layout="normal" tag="tag4">
		<div class="left">
			<p>The final cornerstone of MVC, <strong>views</strong> are the components that deal with presentation,
				typically for a web browser.
			Views generate the information presented to a user, 
				for instance a web page.</p>
				<p>Views are stored inside the application, inside
					<code>application/views</code>, because they are intended
					to have logic in them. If an app has a pure HTML view
					fragment, it could go inside <code>public</code>, and it would
					keep its <code>html</code> filename extension.
				</p>
		</div>
		<div class="right">
			<br/>
			<img class="scale" width="234" height="336" src="/pix/lessons/2/2-10.png"/>
		</div>
	</slide>

	<slide title="View Templates" layout="normal">
		<p>A normal practice is to build a view template, 
			which wraps the "real" webpage body, whose name is 
			passed as a parameter; this is managed by the base controller.</p>
		<p>Such a template is meant to provide a consistent layout across
			a number (perhaps all) of pages in your webapp, with
			placeholders for the pieces appropriate to a given page.</p>
		<p>CI has a "template parser" built-in, which lets us 
			eliminate most PHP script from a view.</p>
			<p>See <code>application/views/_template</code></p>
	</slide>

	<slide title="View Fragments" layout="normal">
		<p>Each of your view fragments would then be stored in its own file, 
			using the substitution fields for passed parameters.</p>
		<p>A view fragment provides a portion or piece of a complete
			page. It is typically well-formed - a complete &lt;div&gt;
			with any nested content.</p>
		<p>Substitution fields are enclosed in braces inside your view file.</p>
		<p>See <code>application/views/homepage</code></p>
	</slide>

	<slide title="View Usage" layout="normal">
		<p>Javascript libraries are not well-supported in CI; 
			you can use them, but effectively client-side.</p>
		<p>Do use CSS to control the appearance.</p>
		<p>Both CSS &amp; Javascript files would be inside your
			<code>public</code> folder, possibly inside appropriate subfolders.
		</p>
		<p>Sample usage: <code>$this-&gt;load-&gt;view('showoff',$data);</code> or 
		<code>$this-&gt;parser-&gt;load('showoff',$data);</code>
		</p>;
	</slide>

 
	<slide title="5. Support Components" layout="normal" tag="tag5">
		<p>An MVC framework comes with a number of pre-built 
			classes or scripts to make your webapp development
			easier and more consistent.</p>
			<p>These are collectively referred to as <strong>support components</strong></p>
			<p>CodeIgniter distinguishes between "libraries" (conventional O-O
			classes) and "helpers" (conventional &amp; global PHP scripts).</p>
	</slide>

	<slide title="Libraries" layout="normal" >
		<div class="left">
			<p>Any classes that you would like to use can be put into 
				the <code>application/libraries</code> folder</p>
				<p>Usage: <code>$this-&gt;load-&gt;library('whatever');</code></p>
			<p>Examples: third party classes, possibly component or entity
				models (similar to JavaBeans)</p>
				<p>The image to the right shows the libraries built into CodeIgniter.
				Some of those, like the Shopping Cart and Javascript libraries,
				have been deprecated, and should not be used.</p>
		</div>
		<div class="right">
			<br/>
			<img class="scale" width="264" height="600" src="/pix/lessons/2/2-11.png"/>
		</div>
	</slide>

	<slide title="Example Library: Product" layout="normal">
		<p>As an example, <code>application/libraries/Product</code>
		could be used as an object model for entities stored in an XML 
			document or RDB table</p>
			<p>
				<code>application/models/Products</code> would be the aggregation of these.</p>
		<p>The reasoning behind such a strategy would be to keep
			entity-level logic separate from the aggregation and persistance logic.
			This is just one way to handle this situation.</p>
	</slide>

	<slide title="Helpers" layout="normal" >
		<div class="left">
			<p>Put your commonly used functions inside a "helper" script</p>
			<p>Our demo app comes with one, to illustrate what this might look
				like ... <code>application/helpers/common_helper</code>.
			</p>
			<p>The "_helper" suffix is a CodeIgniter convention, and this would
			be simply called the "common" helper. Helper file naming follows
			the "words separated by underscores" convention, to reinforce
			that it is "legacy-style" PHP and not object-oriented.</p>
			<p>Our <code>common</code> helper is only meant to be illustrative -
			it does not add needed functionality to the demo app!</p>
		</div>
		<div class="right">
			<br/>
			<img class="scale" width="255" height="246" src="/pix/lessons/2/2-12.png"/>
		</div>
	</slide>

	<slide title="Helpers are &quot;Classic&quot;" layout="normal" >
		<div class="left">
			<p>Usage: <code>$this-&gt;load-&gt;helper('common');</code></p>
			<p>Functions in any such loaded helpers are available everywhere</p>
		</div>
		<div class="right">
			<br/>
			<img class="scale" width="336" height="592" src="/pix/lessons/2/2-13.png"/>
		</div>
	</slide>

	<slide title="6. Your CodeIgniter Webapp" layout="normal" tag="tag6">
		<div class="left">
			<p>Your webapp, including any support components, can
			be extensively configured.</p>
			<p>CodeIgniter provides an <code>application/config</code> folder to 
				let you customize your web app</p>
		</div>
		<div class="right">
			<br/>
			<img class="scale" width="234" height="334" src="/pix/lessons/2/2-14.png"/>
		</div>
	</slide>

	<slide title="Configuration Practices" layout="normal">
		<p>If needed, your front controller <code>index.php</code> needs to be
		modified to correct reference your <code>system</code> folder.
		This has already been done in the demo app.</p>
		<p>The configuration files you are mostly likely to change:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><code>autoload</code> – specify components to load with each request</li>
			<li><code>config</code> – specify application parameters</li>
			<li><code>database</code> – specify RDB parameters</li>
			<li><code>routes</code> – specify default controller</li>
		</ul>
	</slide>

</lesson>
